<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Learning and knowledge recommended to the scholars of Brentwood School in Essex in a sermon preached at their first feast, June 29, 1682 / by William Payne ...</title>
            <author>Payne, William, 1650-1696.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56743</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P904</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32171</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12353063</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12353063</idno>
            <idno type="VID">60042</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56743)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60042)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1025:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Learning and knowledge recommended to the scholars of Brentwood School in Essex in a sermon preached at their first feast, June 29, 1682 / by William Payne ...</title>
                  <author>Payne, William, 1650-1696.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Walter Kettilby ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Learning and scholarship --  England --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:60042:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60042:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>LEARNING AND KNOWLEDGE Recommended to the SCHOLARS OF Brentvvood School In <hi>ESSEX;</hi> IN A SERMON PREACHED At their Firſt FEAST, <hi>June</hi> 29. 1682.</p>
            <p>By <hi>William Payne,</hi> M. A. Rector of St. <hi>Mary White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chappel,</hi> and Fellow of the ROYAL SOCIETY.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed at the earneſt deſire of the <hi>STEWARDS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Walter Kettilby</hi> at the <hi>Biſhop's Head</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 1682.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:60042:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:60042:2"/>
            <head>To his Honoured MASTER, Mr. <hi>Barnard,</hi> of <hi>Brentwood</hi> School in <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AS you were pleaſed to command me this School Exerciſe, which like other Truants you know I was forced to make in haſte, ſo ſince you are reſolved to ſhew it the World I muſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire you to let it know, that you, and the Stewards and thoſe others who heard it, had much better thoughts of it than I my ſelf had, or can yet have the comfort of; and that it goes to the Preſs not out of any wanton inclination it has that way, but meerly to pleaſe its Friends, tho it ſhould happen'd to be ruin'd by it.</p>
            <p>I thought it inconſiſtent with my duty to deny you the firſt fruits however green or raw of your own School, and of what you have ſo great a Title to in the whole; And for your ſake I know all my School-fellows will receive it with kindneſs and candour. 'Twas for their uſe I deſigned it, and calculated it wholly for the Meridian of <hi>Brentwood,</hi> and if any others ſhould chance to read it, and not conſider it was Preach'd
<pb facs="tcp:60042:3"/>chiefly to young Schollars, they may very much injure me, if they will not give me leave to entertain thoſe with ſomething more freedom than I would Mourners at a <hi>Funeral,</hi> and no wiſe and good man can be concern'd to ſee folly and ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>religion expos'd and made ridiculous.</p>
            <p>There is one thing I muſt beg even my School-fellows pardon in, and that is, that I treated them neither with Greek or Latin, but beſides that they are grown diſhes much out of Faſhion at ſuch entertainments, I knew they had enough of thoſe at <hi>Brentwood,</hi> and the School I thought was a more proper place for them than the <hi>Pulpit;</hi> and that they are better afterwards digeſted into ſence than brought up whole again; as <hi>Epictetus,</hi> his Sheep brought their wool and their milk to their Keepers, but not the hay and fodder they had given them. I have no more to ſay for my ſelf, or my <hi>Sermon,</hi> but that both the Preaching and Publiſhing it were deſigned to be ſome way or other ſerviceable to <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Learning,</hi> and to expreſs my grateful reſentments of the kindneſs I have ever received from you, and to aſſure you and the World, that I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute> 
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your moſt obliged and humble Servant,</hi> W. Payne.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:60042:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>PROV. 1.7. latter part</hi> Fools deſpiſe Wiſdom and Inſtruction.</head>
            <p>THoſe who have beſt conſider'd and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood the World, the Ancient as well as the New Philoſophers, have always made one ſyſtem of it, and repreſented it not only as an aggregate and heap of Beings, but as one Compacted and Beautiful, and well compoſed Body, of which we were all the leſſer Parts and Members: And tho they ſeem to have too ſtrait and narrow thoughts of God and his Creation, who think he made the whole Univerſe, the Sun and Moon and whole hoſt of Heaven only for the benefit of this lower <hi>Earth,</hi> this little point in reſpect of the vaſt <hi>expanſum</hi> that is above, yet its more than probable they were all deſigned, and all the numerous creatures in them to be
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:60042:4"/>ſubſervient and uſeful to the whole and to one another, in due proportion and fitneſs they are mutually to correſpond and ſerve each other, and keep ſuch exact harmony as the great <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> has tuned and ordered them for. Mankind 'tis certain were made for mutual help, advantage, and aſſiſtance to each other, &amp; do therefore naturally fall into Societies and combinations that may better promote their own private and the public good; they find it neceſſary to enter into ſeveral Companies and Corporations, that they may carry on all good offices, and beneficiall commerce with one another, &amp; thereby increaſe the common Stock of happineſs in which their own is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded. However the <hi>Hobbiſts</hi> have ſlandered humane nature, and drawn a falſe picture of it from themſelves, and their own ill tempers, and made it a timorous and yet a ravenous Monſter with long fangs and talons, ſharp teeth and claws ready to devour and prey upon its own kind, yet that in it ſelf is very tame and gentle and good natured, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined to love and ſociableneſs, and there is nothing more agreable to it, nor more delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:60042:4"/>than mutual friendſhip and kindneſs; to this Nature has tied us by the firſt and the faſteſt ligaments even thoſe in our Mothers Womb, thoſe <hi>vaſa umbilicalia,</hi> by which we are united to our Parents as well as nouriſh'd by them; and as we cannot be born out of ſociety, and in ſuch a wild ſtate of nature as they would ſuppoſe us, ſo theſe ties of <hi>Birth</hi> and <hi>Bloud</hi> do moſt ſtrongly bind and faſten us together as far as they reach: And the next cement of friendſhip to this of nature, if not a ſtronger, is that of an acquaintance, and ſociety in our firſt tender years, the having our firſt ſprightly Spirits mixt as it were and fermented together. The kind impreſſions that were then made upon us when we were ſoft and fluid, harden afterwards and become firm as in Adamant; like characters cut upon the young and tender bark, they continue and grow greater as the tree increaſes: Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip which is thus early planted in the ſame mold, rootes the deeper, and grows the ſtronger, and is ready ever after to claſp and embrace its old aſſociates with the greateſt confidence and ſatisfaction. 'Tis this Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:60042:5"/>and School-fellows, has brought us here together, and firſt to the Temple and the Houſe of God, the School of all Vertue and <hi>Religion;</hi> that as the Ancients uſed to confirm friendſhip with Sacrifices, and owed Learning and Letters to be the gift and invention of their Gods, and therefore their Prieſts even from the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> were the great preſervers of them, ſo for both thoſe accounts we ſhould begin with <hi>Religion:</hi> And as that is the beſt guaranty of all friendſhip and ſociety, without which they are all but ſo many Treacherous <hi>Aſſociations</hi> againſt Heaven, ſo we cannot ſurely but have a juſt ſence of it when we conſider how Providence in a few years has brought us at leaſt ſome of us, through unſeen ways to our preſent circumſtances and condition; when we ſee the great advantages we have had by the Bleſſing of God, from our firſt early and happy Education, and the great reaſon we have to give Heaven our moſt hearty Thanks, that we were not of the number of <hi>Solomons Fools, who deſpiſe Wiſdom and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:60042:5"/>
            <p>None of thoſe are here, they are without ploding to get mony, they are minding things as they think, of more neceſſary importance, and lading themſelves with thick clay, they are for no wiſdom but with an inheritance, nor for any inſtruction but how to Thrive or grow Rich, they care for nothing further in Grammar than that of <hi>meum</hi> and <hi>tuum,</hi> nor are for any Latin but a <hi>noverint <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſi,</hi> and above all Printing they admire King <hi>Pergamus</hi> his way, the writing upon Parch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and they keep no other Books but ſuch by them, with all the various titles and editi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Leaſes, Morgages, and Purchaſes; and thoſe they are well read in, and underſtand without a Dictionary. And thus with full Pock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets and empty Heads, with Gold in their Bags, perhaps about their Necks, and Lead in their Skulls, theſe laden Aſſes deſpiſe and ſpurn at Learning, becauſe it has not always ſuch Rich trappings as themſelves.</p>
            <p>But the beſt ſort of Tools, they ſay, to get Mony are made of Lead, or at leaſt a great mixture of that Mettal; and the finer Ores are nothing ſo ſerviceable to that purpoſe.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:60042:6"/>
            <p>And there are a ſort of the dulleſt and moſt ſcraping Animals who live always in earth, and have but very little or no eves.</p>
            <p>But there are more Mercuinal Fools, who are abroad Travelling to learn <hi>French</hi> before they can well read or ſpell <hi>Engliſh,</hi> their carefull Mothers thought Latin not ſo good a Language to make a leg with, and that Greek might be apt to make the Child ſtam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, ſo ſhe ſends them early abroad to learn the more important arts of dreſſing and wear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Feathers, of making Court and Addreſs; and ſo their Learning ever after lyes in comb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Wiggs, and putting on their Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vats, and they prove eternall Students upon their own Looking-glaſſes; they ſhrug and throw their Heads modiſhly, and tread much more exactly than they think; but all Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they contemn, becauſe 'tis bald and weares ruff, and cannot fancy the Muſes becauſe they are ill dreſt; with great judgment they prefer a <hi>French</hi> face before <hi>Virgil</hi> and <hi>Homer,</hi> and ſee more wit in <hi>Scaramouchies</hi> face than in all the Antients put together, and deſpiſe all the Greek and the Roman Hiſtories in reſpect of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:60042:6"/>the amours of the <hi>French</hi> Court. One of theſe men would fain be an Atheiſt but he has not skill to read <hi>Lucretius,</hi> and ſo is fain to be a ſmall retailer at Atheiſm and Prophaneneſs, as he picks it up in little parcells from a Play or a Lampoon; and that we may be well aſſured that he deſpiſes nothing like Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unleſs it be <hi>Religion,</hi> he thinks nothing in the World ſo contemptible as a Parſon and a School-maſter, and next to himſelf he thinks nothing ſo accompliſh'd as a Dancing-maſter or a Player, and who of all theſe is the worthier man we muſt leave it as a diſpute among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. But leſt ſhowing you the Picture of theſe Fooles ſhould make us too merry, let us ſeriouſly conſider the reall good and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency that accrues from that Wiſdom and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction that they deſpiſe, and I ſhall endae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to repreſent that to you upon theſe four accounts.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. As it improves a mans own mind.</item>
               <item>2. As it fits him to do good in the World.</item>
               <item>3. As it entertains a mans Time and his Life with the greateſt pleaſure.</item>
               <item>4. As it is uſefull to the concerns of <hi>Religion.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:60042:7"/>
            <p n="1">1. As it improves a mans own mind. It is a very probable opinion of the Wiſeſt men and Philoſophers, that humane Souls are all equal, that Nature like a juſt and impartial Mother, as ſhe has made us all out of the ſame clay, the ſame Fleſh and Bloud, ſo ſhe has equally divided Reaſon and Underſtanding amongſt us as a common Portion, and given us intellectuall powers and faculties of the ſame ſize and bigneſs, and that which makes them ſo much differ at ſo great a rate, that the ſouls of ſome men ſeem to be at as high a pitch above the loweſt of others, as they do above the beſt ſort of Brutes, is beſides the various temperament of the Body and contex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Brain from their Education. 'Tis this which cultivates and improves the Soil into Riches and Fruitfulneſs, that would all without it be barren and wilderneſs; and carves &amp; works the ſame wood into a piece fit to adorn the Temple of God, or the Palaces of Princes, that would elſe have bin but an heavy block, and uſeleſs log: As Naturaliſts tell us thoſe active and ſpirituous parts that are in moſt Bodies are lock'd up and impriſon'd un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:60042:7"/>they are freed and unlooſed by heat and ſuch like exaltations; ſo that reaſon which is in human minds ſunk and oppreſt with heavy matter is to be excited &amp; ſublimed by a courſe of ſtudy and learned preparations; and this it is ſometimes in ſo high a degree, that the ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Spirits of wit and reaſon have bin drawn off from the lees as it were of mankind and the loweſt parts; and ſome who gave no man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of promiſes at firſt, yet by means of a kindly Education have blown and ripen'd tho perhaps more ſlowly, yet to conſiderable improvements; ſo that one would think that theſe after they became Proſelytes to Learning had as the <hi>Jews</hi> imagin'd of the Profelytes to their <hi>Religion,</hi> a New ſoul put into them.</p>
            <p>Reaſon is the greateſt perfection of humane Nature, but like a Diamond it is naturally rough until Education poliſh and well ſet it, and without that we ſee how it ſinks into brutiſh ſottiſhneſs in the untaught and uncivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lized part of mankind.</p>
            <p>There can be nothing ſo perfective of our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, ſo much worth our utmoſt care and deſires as a wiſe and well improved mind, a
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:60042:8"/>defect of reaſon and underſtanding is the greateſt blemiſh of humane nature beyond that of the worſt deformity; and their is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo low and contemptible in the opinion of every one as to be a Fool and a Block-head; he that can endure if not boaſt himſelf to be Vitious and Debaucht cannot bear that, and tho our age has endeavored as much as it can to make vice creditable, and leſſen the vertuous and morall improvements of the mind, yet it has kept ſo much of humanity as to give the greateſt Honour, even above every thing elſe, to wit and good underſtanding.</p>
            <p>And what is that, but a filling the mind with true conceptions and lively idaeas, the ſtoring and enriching it with the beſt knowledg of things, and the moſt curious Images and Pictures of them, the enlarging and open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it to the Nobleſt truths, and letting it ſee and behold all things that God and Nature has ſet round about it.</p>
            <p>Theſe are ſome crawling Souls that look only downward, and mind nothing but what is juſt under their feet, Creatures that are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd no further than their own ſtye and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:60042:8"/>troughr, and have no larger compaſs for their thoughts than the kennell they ſleep in; and how ſhrunk and little do their minds grow, how do they ſhrivel and dry up to nothing; I will not ſay how ill was reaſon beſtow'd upon them, but how ill do they uſe that greateſt gift of God to men, and hide that noble Talent in a Dunghill. How is their ſoul only like Salt to keep their Body ſweet, and preſerve the hog from ſtinking; how would it tempt one to think that was even ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial, and like the <hi>anima brutorum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It has been the conceit of many that the ſoul is but a <hi>raſa tabula,</hi> a kind of fair unwrit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Paper till it has received impreſſions from without, and in theſe men it continues a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect blank, or at leaſt 'tis onely a little ſeroled with ſome odd marks, and here and there blot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and blur'd over; 'Tis onely Wiſdom and Inſtruction that fill it with fair and excellent Characters, that writ things upon it in their natural ſhape and order, that draw them to the Life, and in their true colours and poſtures, and deſcribe upon it the greateſt remarques and concerns that are or have been in the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:60042:9"/>World: And by theſe means make it inſtead of a dark and hollow Cave, fill'd only with damps &amp; ugly ſpectres, a pleaſant and delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Store-houſe of the richeſt truth and the choiceſt knowledg.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As it fits a man to do good i'the World, and I think it deſerves not the name of Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom that does not ſome way or other do that; if a mans Learning be only about toyes and trifles, however odd and pretty he may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trive them, and be not an inſtrument that will ſerve to any uſefull purpoſes for man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind; if inſtead of making a little City great with <hi>Themiſtocles,</hi> it teach him only to play on the fiddle; if it be only a critical knowing words without things, a making Elymologies and Cognations with thoſe that are no way related, a contriving nice terms and diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to looſe plain ſence, a ſtudying Judiciary Schemes, and fancifull Cabalas, and myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <hi>Zoars,</hi> 'tis then onely a more Learned ſort of folly and ignorance; he that Studies hard only for thoſe things, is much like him that ſhould Travel over a great part of the World to make a collection of the tayls of Monkeys, or the fins of flying Fiſhes. Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:60042:9"/>is like to be more benefited by the labors of a Porter, or a Ploughman, than by ſuch tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling and uſeleſs pedantry: But thoſe things which are moſt beneficial to the World, which really conduce to the comfort, and welfare, and happineſs of Mankind, are beſt carried on by the help of the trueſt Learning, and beſt Knowlege; Phyſick that preſerves our health, and reſtores it, is founded in natural Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege and Phyloſophy; Navigation that brings us all the Conveniences and Riches of the World in Aſtronomy and Geometry, the knowlege of Law and Government upon that of Ancient Codes and Hiſtories, as well as modern; and Divinity it ſelf upon almoſt all others, and eſpecially the knowlege of true Moralls, of Tongues, and Eccleſiaſtical Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity; without which, inſtead of Phyſicians and Merchants, we ſhould have only Mounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banks and Pedlars; and inſtead of Lawyers and Divines, only Pettifoggers and Divinity Quacks.</p>
            <p>And in all things whatſoever the more dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous and ready and nimble any part is, the more ſubſervient will it be to the uſes of the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:60042:10"/>whole Body; and Knowlege in general is the ſame thing to Practice that Sight is to Walking, it ſhews us the realities of things, and diſpells the ſhadows and falſe conceptions of them, and lets us ſee how to handle and take right hold of them, and manage them by the trueſt meaſures of Prudence; it ſets us in the right and neareſt way to ſuch an end, and lets us ſee the difficulties before us, and the beſt means to eſcape them; it regulates us in our practice by right rules and methods, and manages and orders all circumſtances to ſute beſt with the deſign it propoſes; &amp; tho ſome men who are carried into the ſhady and ſolitary parts of Knowlege and Speculation, are by diſuſe rendred unfit for an active Life, yet where Learning and Knowlege, and an active Mind happen to meet, 'tis they that do the great things, and much greater in ſuch a conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction than they could do aſunder; and tho without that we have ſome inſtances of uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full men, and great exploits, yet 'tis but as we have of great Cures done by Empirics, 'tis good Skill joyn'd with Experience that is much more valuable.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:60042:10"/>
            <p>The moſt uſeful perſons to Mankind have bin the men of Wiſdom and Learning, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs not only the Inventers of Arts &amp; Letters, the <hi>Egyptian Thoth</hi> or <hi>Hermes,</hi> the <hi>Grecian Orpheus</hi> and <hi>Palamedes,</hi> and other celebrated names, but the beſt Law-givers that have made whole Kingdoms happy by their Wiſe inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>Licurgus,</hi> and <hi>Solon,</hi> and <hi>Numa;</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all <hi>Moſes,</hi> brought up in all the Learning of the <hi>Egyptians;</hi> and to the honour of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and thoſe who have been the Teachers of it, it is obſerv'd that where Princes have had the fortune of good Tutors and Inſtructors, they have made themſelves and their King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes both great; Such as <hi>Charles</hi> the Great who had <hi>Alcuinus</hi> for his Maſter, a Diſciple of <hi>Bede; Honorius</hi> and <hi>Arcadius</hi> who had <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenius, Otho</hi> the Emperor who had <hi>Gilbertus Floriacenſis,</hi> and <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth who had <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drian</hi> the Sixth; and ſo ſenſible were thoſe great men of the benefits they had by their Education, that in gratitude to their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, ſome procured Statues for them; as <hi>Mark Antony</hi> did for <hi>Junius Ruſticus,</hi> and <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian</hi> the Emperor made his Tutor <hi>Auſonius</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:60042:11"/>Conſul, and <hi>Alexander</hi> own'd himſelf as much obliged to <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> as to <hi>Philip</hi> his Father.</p>
            <p>The happineſs of <hi>Rome</hi> under <hi>Nero</hi>'s mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nority is juſtly aſcribed to <hi>Seneca,</hi> and that of <hi>Gordianus</hi> to his Tutor <hi>Miſitheus;</hi> and this obſervation is true, both nearer us at home, and as far back as <hi>Joſeph</hi> and <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> and the foundation of the <hi>Italian</hi> Common-wealths by <hi>Zaleucus</hi> and <hi>Charondas,</hi> who were the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> juſtifying that ſaying of <hi>Plato,</hi> that thoſe Common-wealth's were hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py where either Philoſophers govern'd, or their Governors Philoſophized: And 'tis cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain thoſe Kingdoms have been always the moſt famous even for Arms too, who have been ſo for Learning and Sciences, and when <hi>Rome</hi> decayed in the latter of theſe, it did in the former; and was over-run by the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous and Northern Nations, when it was it ſelf growing barbarous.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I ſhall conſider the excellency of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Knowlege, as it entertains a mans life, and his time with the greateſt pleaſure: Thus Knowlege like Light is not only uſeful and neceſſary to the doing buſineſs, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:60042:11"/>tranſacting our affairs, but 'tis infinitely plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant and delightful in it ſelf, and were it on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo, it were no way to be deſpiſed; as no man would be willing to be blind, tho he had not much to do.</p>
            <p>Our minds are buſy and active things, apt to be wearied and tired with the ſame objects, and can quickly exhauſt all the ſweetneſs and vertue out of them, and muſt be ſtill in queſt of freſh entertainment for themſelves; or elſe like cloy'd and ſurfeited Stomachs they will turn all they have into <hi>nauſea</hi> and loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and 'tis Knowlege alone that can feed them with new dainties &amp; repaſts, and furniſh them with infinite variety of ſound &amp; manly pleaſures, that ſhall never grow flat and lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guid, nor ſatiate and overcome us.</p>
            <p>'Tis certain there is no appetite more ſtrong, nor the fatisfaction of it more pleaſant than that of Knowlege, the thirſt of it increaſes with drinking, and yet every ſip and taſte is extreme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly delicious, and has tranſported even Wiſe men beyond Wine, or Raptures; with great ardor and <hi>impetus</hi> does our minds court and embrace it, and find infinite pleaſure in every
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:60042:12"/>enjoyment of it, and all its conceptions are brought forth, if not with eaſe, yet with joy and ecſtaſie; ſo that whole hecatombs have been offered at the birth of a new notion, or piece of knowledge; more was <hi>Archimedes</hi> tranſported with his Problem, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, than the Prieſts, or others, at their moſt jovial <hi>Bacchanals:</hi> And not only in ſome ſudden rapturous effects does it outdoe all the lower pleaſures of Senſuality, but it entertains the mind with a calm and even, a laſting and abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding pleaſure, or rather a conſtant variety of pleaſures. What can more divert and pleaſe our thoughts than to look back ſometimes upon the Ages that are paſt, to acquaint one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with the tranſactions and affairs that have buſied the world, to view the diſtant Scenes, and the thronged Theater of Ancient times, and conſider all the Parts of the great Fable and <hi>Drama</hi> that Mankind has been ever act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and not to be always Children, as <hi>Tully</hi> calls it, and know only what is preſent and in their days; or at furtheſt, have no other Hiſtory than at the beginning of an Alma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nack: I will not mention the pleaſure of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:60042:12"/>looking forwards to Ages to come, tho the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate deſire of that ſhows how pleaſant even the forbidden Fruits of the Tree of Knowlege are, but without the help either of Stars or Familiars, a Wiſe man may make ſuch conjectures of Futurity as are uſeful to him, and the wiſe obſerving what is paſt, is the beſt Scheme can be erected to know what is to come.</p>
            <p>How delightful is it ſafely to travel over all the Earth, the great Cities and the vaſt Mountains, the mighty Deep and the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Plains and Rivers, and take a proſpect of the whole and large Field of Nature, and all the variety upon it; to converſe now and then with the wiſeſt Nations, and with the barbarous, and ſee their Cuſtoms and Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and whatever is worthy a curious en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry. How pleaſant is it to Survey the whole beautiful and regular frame of the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſe, to look into the ſecret treaſuries of the Earth, to ſee its fruitfull Bowels diſſected and laid open before us, all the riches of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ranſack'd in its Mines and Minerals, and to have a view of all its choice Pieces and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Draughts, and underſtand the fine and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:60042:13"/>curious way by which it works them; to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into its Laboratory, and ſee the courſe of Chymiſtry it goes through in every Animals body, and the wonderful Mechaniſm of every Part and Member; to look into our ſelves, and ſee the delicate Clock-work that moves our Hands and our Feet, and the fine lay'd Pipes and Water-works that convey the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> and the Blood and Spirits from their proper Conduits: Nay to aſcend into the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Heavens, and with a quick and nimble thought paſs through all the Spheres and <hi>Vor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tices,</hi> and ſee how they are made, and in what Lines they move; what Order and Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony they keep, and how the great Geome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter has made all things in Weight and Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, with the beſt counſel and contrivance: What can be equal to all theſe pleaſures of Wonder and Admiration, Learning and Knowledge? This is one of the nobleſt Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainments that God deſigned man to enjoy in this World, to contemplate the Works of the Creation, and 'tis one of thoſe Pleaſures which God himſelf enjoy'd, when he ſurvey d his own Creation, and ſaw that it was Good; and agreable to the idaeas of his own wiſe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:60042:13"/>mind; there are none but muſt be ſenſible of this, unleſs a groſs Ignorance ſpoil their <hi>Palate,</hi> and like the <hi>Chaonian</hi> Clown, they care for no other Meat or Entertainment but <hi>Acorns,</hi> and what they have been uſed to in there own <hi>Cottage,</hi> and think nothing reliſhes with any true guſto, but rank Garlick and Onions.</p>
            <p n="4">4. I ſhall conſider the Good and Execllency of Learning as it is uſeful to the concerns of <hi>Religion,</hi> and then it becomes the trueſt Wiſdom, when it has any tendency, any way to ſerve <hi>Religion,</hi> without which we are Fools in the main, and ſhall be found ſo at laſt, and at the foot of the account.</p>
            <p>There are ſome indeed, that think Learning an Enemy to <hi>Religion,</hi> and that 'tis better bred up under a devout Ignorance, And then <hi>Heathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm,</hi> would have been a better Mother of Devotion then <hi>Chriſtianity;</hi> but whatever thoughts theſe Men have of Learning which we ſhall ſee anon, <hi>I</hi> am afraid they have no great kindneſs for <hi>Religion,</hi> 'tis to be feared they have no good deſigns upon it who thus keep it in the dark, 'tis there they Proſtitute
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:60042:14"/>and corrupt it, and make it yield to their baſe, lewd, and villanous deſigns, and indeed ſuch a thing as they have made of it, the only way to make men devoutly adore it, is not to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it; the Light would betray their falſe wares, and diſcover the baſe Coyn they would put off, however Infallibility have ſtampt and counterfeited it: but theſe men and their friends are often crying out againſt too many Schools, and too much Learning, as the means to make men pert and conceited, eternal diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in Religion, ſetters up of ſects and parties, and ſo think themſelves wiſer than their Teachers, or their Governours; If they do ſo, I am ſure 'tis the fault of their Ignorance, and not of their Learning; all thoſe miſchiefs proceed not from having, but wanting a good underſtanding; and I am afraid the leſſening <hi>Schools,</hi> and ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Learning, is not the beſt way to remedy that; but as one of the wiſeſt Enemies to <hi>Chriſtianity, Julian,</hi> thought this the moſt likely way utterly to deſtroy it. And if Princes muſt uſe this way to keep their People quiet and orderly, then to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent mutinies and quarelling, and ſeditious break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Peace; they may as well blindfold them
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:60042:14"/>or put out their eyes, by which they would be forced to live quietly, but things are come to a very hard paſs if men muſt become a ſort of ſtupid brutes, that they may be the better manag'd, and in order to bear the bit and bridle, muſt not exerciſe and improve their Reaſon: 'Tis certain if they had not Eyes, nor Hands, nor Legs, they would not be ſo well fitted to do miſchief, but no more would they likewiſe to do good, and therefore 'tis not adviſable to deſtroy a manifeſt good thing, for an accidental inconvenience that may ſometimes happen from it, not with the <hi>Thracians</hi> to cut down all the Vines in their Countrey to avoid Drunkenneſs, nor with the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> and the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Policy, to deſtroy Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Knowledge, to make men more Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable and Religious. But becauſe if Learning were any way prejudicial to Religion, all its other uſes and excellencies, would ſignifie very little, and it would be improper for me to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend it to you in this place, I ſhall par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly ſhew its manifeſt uſefulneſs to that, as it deſtroys the greateſt Enemies to it, which are theſe: <hi>Atheiſm, Prophaneſs, Popery</hi> and <hi>Fanati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:60042:15"/>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Atheiſm,</hi> and yet that has been laid to the Charge of being great Scholars, but very unjuſtly, tho' we ſhould reckon <hi>Epicurus, Vaninus,</hi> and <hi>Hobbs,</hi> among the <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> 'tis certain, they were none of the great Clerks of their Age, and 'twas chiefly their ſingularity and boldneſs to confront the natural ſenſe, and univerſal opinion of all wiſe men, that made them conſiderable or taken notice of, they might have paſt elſe unobſerv'd, and unregarded in the common crowd: and we very well know, that moſt of their Followers in our Age can ſcarce underſtand, and often are not able to read them, unleſs for the common benefit of <hi>Atheiſm,</hi> they are tranſlated into their Mothers Tongue; and by thoſe helps he that reſolves to be lew'd and debaucht, thinks it beſt to ſet up for a wit and an <hi>Athieſt,</hi> and to laugh at the Contradiction of ſpiritual Subſtances, and immaterial beings, and he can concieve nothing but matter and motion, and will not let the Prieſts inpoſe any thing upon him, that he can't underſtand; but had this man but a little more Learning and Senſe, he would preſently find, that 'tis as eaſie to underſtand ſpirit as matter, and that there are nigh as many difficulties in
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:60042:15"/>the moſt ordinary <hi>Phaenomina</hi> of Nature, as in the Myſteries of <hi>Religion,</hi> and that he can as little give a full Account of the moſt obvious things, the colour of graſs, or his own hair, the natural paints of Flowers, the Species and Seeds of Fruits, his own Figure, Shape, and the like; as how Spirits think, and move, and converſe without a Body; and that a Man may as much loſe himſelf in thoſe things the further he goes on, and muſt at laſt ſtop at the Will of the Firſt Cauſe, as in the other; and 'tis as eaſie to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive an infinite God, as infinite Matter or Space, and how he is preſent in all places and yet has no parts, as how Matter is made either of divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibles or indiviſibles, how the Center is equal to the Circumference, and how two Lines may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach nearer one another? and yet never touch, tho' drawn in <hi>infinitum:</hi> ſo much Learning as will make a good Philoſopher will ſpoil an <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> and the right knowledge of Nature; will bring him to the knowledge of a God, when he ſees in every part of it the footſteps not of Chance, but of wiſe Counfel; and by conſidering that, he will find the nature of good and evil to be as certain and immutable, as
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:60042:16"/>that of a Circle or triangle: and if he go on to read Books, he will find that all the wiſe Men that ever were in the world, have been againſt <hi>Atheiſm,</hi> that the belief of a God has been the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of all ages and nations, of the wiſeſt and the freeſt thinkers, as well as the unlearned and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, and that there have been few ſuch Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Men as have denyed it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Prophaneſs and debauchery, which you have obſerv'd I am ſure the ſmalleſt proficients in Learning, and the moſt idle truants from their Book, to be moſt apt to fall into; Alas 'tis much more eaſy to diſcourſe looſly and idely, then coherently and to the purpoſe, to be fluent in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhionable oaths then in any true eloquence, to talk Ribauldry and Prophaneſs, than ſence and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; and therefore you ſhall often find, that he who could hardly be brought to conſtrue <hi>Cato</hi> at School, ſhall afterwards out of ſpite and revenge, deſpiſe and laugh at all Vertue and Morality; and he who could never read the Greek <hi>Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> ſhall become a notable Jeſter up the Bible in <hi>Engliſh;</hi> and the raw and ſimple Fop, that has not the Learning of the meaneſt <hi>Curate,</hi> ſhall be confidently drolling upon God and Religion, and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:60042:16"/>exerciſing his wit and railery, ſuch as it is, upon all the Learned Men in black; Now had this witty dunce ever had the skill or the patience, to Study and know what Learning was, he would have had more eſteem for it where e're it is, and have known how to put it to a better uſe. And tho' I ſhall not reckon either Greek or Latin, no nor Hebrew, neither <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> or <hi>Cartes,</hi> or <hi>Averroes,</hi> among the Inſtruments of Converſion, or the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary means of Grace; yet I am confident that the applying a Mans mind to ſtudy, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploying it in the buſineſs of Learning and Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, will both take him off and divert him from moſt of that lewdneſs and debauchery, that idle and unemploy'd and active minds fall into; and will help to fix the quick-ſilver, and ſettle the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travegancies they are inclined to; and turn that looſe, and wild, and frothy humour, which is the uſual vehicle of Prophaneneſs and effect of Idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, into ſolid and conſiſtent Senſe and Learning; and that is the beſt prepared ſeed-plot and nurſery for true <hi>Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Popery,</hi> which ſprang up in the darkeſt, and moſt barbarous Ages of Chriſtianity; in the Night when men were aſleep, the Enemy ſow'd
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:60042:17"/>thoſe tares in the Church that have ſince over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>run the true Corn; when Learning degenerated into fabulous Legends, and Monkiſh Stories, when it was ſuſpected to be a good Latiniſt, and almoſt Hereſy to underſtand Greek; then they foiſted in thoſe falſe and ſpurious Readings into the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients, and put out feigned Books under falſe Names, and took the advantage of an ignorant and undiſcerning Age, as diſhoneſt perſons do of the Night, or the duskiſh twilight; and when it was become an Hereſy to believe the <hi>Antipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des,</hi> it was a good time to make <hi>Purgatory,</hi> or <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> an Article of Faith; and even now in thoſe Countrys which are the trueſt vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals to the <hi>Popedom,</hi> the decay of Learning is very manifeſt, ſo that there is little of Greek in <hi>Italy,</hi> and ſcarce any at all in <hi>Spain,</hi> the <hi>Scool-Men</hi> and the <hi>Canoniſts,</hi> making up almoſt all the Learning amongſt them, and 'tis not to be dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bted that the reſtoring Learning by <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> and others about his time, made great way for the Reformation, and diſpoſed the world very much to receive it; and that Learning, and free Phyloſophy, and exammination of things which has been the temper of the world ever ſince, has
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:60042:17"/>not a little thratened and affrighted them, and they ſufficiently ſhow'd their diſlike of it in the uſage of <hi>Galileo:</hi> it being their whole deſign to keep Mens minds in Ignorance and Captivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, in Darkneſs and Slavery, and by no means to allow that liberty of thinking, and reaſoning, of enquiring, examining and judging, which the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation</hi> doth.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Learning as 'tis an Enemy to <hi>Popery</hi> ſo 'tis no friend to <hi>Faniticiſm,</hi> every one knows, that grows out of an unskilful Head that has great heat in it but without light; <hi>Enthuſiaſm</hi> is a kind of Spiritual Frenzy and Religious madneſs, that proceeds from a great Zeal that puts the Blood and Spirits into an Extraordinary Ferment and Commotion, and has but very little knowledg to ſlake and cool, and govern them; and next to the Applications of <hi>Phyſick</hi> and letting Blood, there is nothing will ſo certainly cure it as ſober Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Inſtruction; this clears the mind of all thoſe fumes that diſturb it, and diſpells thoſe dark Images and Repreſentations of things that are before it, all thoſe <hi>Phantaſms</hi> and <hi>Chime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras</hi> like Sprites and <hi>Hobgoblins</hi> vaniſh at the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of Light and Day, and hant and diſturb
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:60042:18"/>People only in the dark. The Enthuſiaſts and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders to Inſpirations, have been always the great decryers of Humane Learning under the name of vain Philoſophy, as being ſenſible that nothing does more tend to abate the exceſſes and allay the violences of their <hi>Enthuſiaſtick</hi> Fervors, then this doth, and then I am ſure nothing can be more ſerviceable to <hi>Religion</hi> than that which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents one of the worſt deſeaſes it is ſubject to, A Spiritual <hi>Hectick</hi> and Conſumption.</p>
            <p>I ſhall crave leave to add but one thing more to ſhow not only the ſerviceableneſs but the abſolute neceſſity of Learning to <hi>Religion,</hi> and that is this, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> that was taught by God, and deliver'd from Heaven is contain'd and tranſmitted down to us in ſuch Books and Records as do neceſſarily require Learning to underſtand them, not only the skill in Languages as a Key to unlock and decypher the meaning of thoſe Holy Books, and the peculiar <hi>Idiotiſms</hi> and <hi>Proprieties</hi> of thoſe Languages, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which we have only the ſound and not the ſence of them, but the knowledg of Times and of Places, and the Cuſtoms and Manners of thoſe People to whom many things in Holy <hi>Scripture</hi> do imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately relate, and their true meaning cannot be
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:60042:18"/>underſtood without them; one of the great Cauſes of miſ-interpreting, and miſtaking the ſenſe of Holy Scripture, is the taking it as a Book writ in our Times, and not many Ages ago, and the thinking nothing neceſſary to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand and manage the Bible, but a vulgar Tranſlation, and a large Concordance; when ſome of the moſt conſiderable things in it, not only the Propheſies of the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> and the time of his coming, but the nature of the two Sacraments nay that of our Saviour's Sacrifice and ſatisfaction, cannot well be underſtood without knowing the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> and the Heathen Notion about Sacrifices, and yet 'tis that upon which the whole <hi>Goſpel oeconomy</hi> does mightily depend. Indeed the great and neceſſary lines of Morality are ſo plain not only there, but even on the hearts of all Men that they need not much Comment; but the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding all the parts of thoſe Holy Books, (part of which is the moſt antient Writing we know of) and all the ſeveral Revelations and particular matters contained in them, is a Work of the greateſt and the moſt valuable Learning.</p>
            <p>But I ſhall add no more but my earneſt advice and wiſhes that we who have had the advantage
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:60042:19"/>of Learning and good Education, would take care to employ it ſome way or other to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes of <hi>Religion,</hi> and bring ſome honor and advantage to that by it.</p>
            <p>And as 'tis the moſt ill Manners and ill Breed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not to treat <hi>Religion,</hi> the moſt ſacred thing in the World with decency and reſpect, ſo 'tis a ſign of little Wit and leſs Learning not to believe it, and then 'tis the greareſt folly i'the World not to practice it, unleſs it be that of Buffooning and Burleſquing it, and therefore let us take care to leave all thoſe rude and unmannerly, as well as mad and wicked things, to thoſe Atheiſtical and Prophane, <hi>Popiſh</hi> and Fanatical Fools, who are thoſe chiefly who deſpiſe Wiſdom and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:60042:19"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
